Guide to the South Brooklyn Savings Bank records 2007.001
Brooklyn Historical Society
South Brooklyn Savings Bank records
1850-2006
1850-1980
Brooklyn Historical Society
Independence Savings Bank (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
South Brooklyn Savings Institution (New York, N.Y.)
Independence Community Bank (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
South Brooklyn Savings Bank
2007.001
38 Linear Feet in 60 boxes of various sizes and five loose objects
The collection consists of the records of the Board of Trustees of the South Brooklyn Savings Bank (originally known as the South Brooklyn Savings Institution, and later known as the Independence Savings Bank and the Independence Community Bank). These records include Board meeting minutes, financial records and reports, administrative files, photographs, scrapbooks, and memorabilia. The records span the entire history of the bank, from its founding in 1850 through 2006 (the year the bank was acquired by Sovereign Bank).
Historical Note
The South Brooklyn Savings Institution was found in Brooklyn, NY, in 1850. The institution formally channged its name to the South Brooklyn Savings Bank in 1930. The bank's main branch was located at the corner of Atlantic Avenue and Court Street. Another major branch was located at 18th Avenue and 65th Street. In 1975, the bank formally changed its name to the Independence Savings Bank. In 1992, "the bank reorganized into [a] mutual holding company." The bank underwent further reorganization 1997, and formally changed its name to Independence Community Bank Corp. Finally, the bank was acquired by Soveriegn Bank in 2006.
Independence Community Bank was founded in Brooklyn, N.Y. in 1850 as The South Brooklyn Savings Institution. It was bought out by Sovereign Bank in 2006. After the buyout, the Brooklyn Historical Society, with the support of the Independence Community Foundation (now the Brooklyn Community Foundation), conducted 16 extended interviews with past and present employees of Independence Community Bank to document the end of the Bank's 155 years based in Brooklyn.
The South Brooklyn Savings Institution was founded in Brooklyn, New York, in 1850. The institution formally changed its name to the South Brooklyn Savings Bank in 1930. The bank's main branch was located at the corner of Atlantic Avenue and Court Street. Another major branch was located at 18th Avenue and 65th Street. The bank expanded throughout the 20th century, with offices located in Brooklyn, Queens, Manhattan, the Bronx, and Nassau County, New York. In 1975, the bank formally changed its name to the Independence Savings Bank. In 1992, "the bank reorganized into [a] mutual holding company." The bank underwent further reorganization in 1997, and formally changed its name to Independence Community Bank Corp. In 2006, the bank was acquired by Sovereign Bancorp, Inc.
Sources
South Brooklyn Savings Bank One Hundredth Anniversary booklet, 1950
Certificate of name change, 1930
Independence Savings Bank financial statement, 1975
Independence Community Bank Corp. - U.S. Securities and Exchange Commission report, 2000
Arrangement
The collection is organized into five series:
Series 1: Board of Trustees meeting minutes
Series 2: Financial records
Series 3: Administrative files
Series 4: Photographs and Scrapbooks
Series 5: Memorabilia
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of the records of the Board of Trustees of the South Brooklyn Savings Bank (originally known as the South Brooklyn Savings Institution, and later known as the Independence Savings Bank and the Independence Community Bank). These records include Board meeting minutes, financial records and reports, administrative files, photographs, scrapbooks, and memorabilia. The records span the entire history of the bank, from its founding in 1850 through 2006 (the year the bank was acquired by Sovereign Bank).
Conditions Governing Access
Open to users without restriction.
Related Materials
Brooklyn Historical Society holds the following related collections:
Missing Title
Independence Community Bank oral histories, 2006-2007 (2008.032)
South Brooklyn Savings Institution trustees photographic portrait albums, 1850-1922 (ARC.215).
Independence Community Bank Presidential Portrait Collection, 1850-1973 (M2007.023)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Independence Community Bank Corp., 2007.
Awards; Sports -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Business records; Baseballs (ball); Reports; Bowling |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Trophies (objects); Advertising |x Banks and banking; Clippings (information artifacts); Scrapbooks; Tax records; Minutes; Ephemera; Deeds; Financial records; Financial statements; Mortgages |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Baseball |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Basketball |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Savings banks |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Portraits; Artifacts (object genre); Banks and banking |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community banks |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Interviews; Sound recordings; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Commerce; Annual reports; Photographs; Bank employees |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Sovereign Bancorp; South Brooklyn Savings Institution (New York, N.Y.); Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation; Independence Community Bank (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); South Brooklyn Savings Bank; Independence Savings Bank (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
- Series 1: Board of Trustees and Committee meeting minutes, 1850-1966; 15052
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains Board of Trustee meeting minutes, dating from the 1850s through the 1960s. Executive Committee meeting minutes (1877-1966) document the decision-making and policies which led to the bank's success and expansion from 1850 to 1966. This series also include minutes from the Finance, Investment, and Buildings committees.
  - Board of Trustees meeting minutes (2 volumes), 1850-1917; 15074 (Box 14, Folder -)
  - Board of Trustees meeting minutes, 1917-1933; 15073 (Box 13, Folder -)
  - Board of Trustees meeting minutes, 1933-1935; 15064 (Box 9, Folder -)
  - SBSB Board of Trustees Minutes, 1938-1953 (Box 52)
  - SBSB Board of Trustees Minutes, 1953-1960 (Box 53)
  - SBSB Board of Trustees Minutes, 1960-1964 (Box 54)
  - SBSB Board of Trustees Minutes, 1965-1973 (Box 55)
  - SBSB Board of Trustees Minutes, 1973-1975 (Box 56)
  - Notarized Board Reports, 1936-1950 (Box 27, Folder 1-5)
  - Notarized Board Reports, 1951-1955 (Box 28, Folder 1-3)
  - Notarized Board Reports, 1956-1958 (Box 29, Folder 8)
  - Board Reports, 1959 (Box 44, Folder 8)
  - Board Reports, 1960-1961 (Box 45, Folder 1-4)
  - Board Reports, 1963 (Box 46, Folder 2)
  - Executive Committee meeting minutes, 1877-1920; 15065 (Box 9)
  - Executive Committee meeting minutes, 1958-1966; 15053 (Box 8)
  - SBSB Executive Committee Minutes No. 14, 1949-1950 (Box 59)
  - SBSB Executive Committee Minutes No. 15, 1950-1958 (Box 60)
  - Executive Committee Reports, 1961-1964 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Executive Committee Reports, 1965-1968 (Box 31, Folder 1)
  - Report to Executive Committee, 1969-1970 (Box 31, Folder 2-4)
  - Executive Committee Supplemental Minutes, 1951-1955 (Box 42, Folder 1-5)
  - Executive Committee Supplemental Minutes, 1956-1958 (Box 43, Folder 1-3)
  - Executive Committee Reports, 1959-1960 (Box 49, Folder 3)
  - SBSB Finance Committee Minutes, 1933-1937 (Box 57)
  - SBSB Finance Committee Minutes No. 8, 1937-1938 (Box 57)
  - SBSB Finance Committee Minutes No. 9, 1938-1940 (Box 58)
  - SBSB Finance Committee Minutes No. 10, 1940-1942 (Box 58)
  - SBSB Finance Committee Minutes No. 11, 1942-1944 (Box 58)
  - SBSB Finance Committee Minutes No. 12, 1944-1946 (Box 59)
  - SBSB Finance Committee Minutes No. 13, 1946-1948 (Box 59)
  - Independence Savings Bank Board of Trustees Minutes, 1975-1978 (Box 56)
  - Life Insurance Report to The Board Of Trustees, 1959-1964 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Mortgage Officer Report andTreasurer's Report to Board of Trustees, 1965-1967 (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Board Of Trustees and Mortgage Office's Reports and Treasurer Reports, 1959-1960 (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - Treasurer's Reports and Mortgage Officer' s Reports, 1961-1962 (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - Mortgage Officer's Report and Treasurer's Report to The Board of Trustees, 1963-1964 (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - Life Insurance Report to The Board Of Trustees, 1950-1958 (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - Reports to Board of Trustees Finance Committee, 1933-1934 (Box 30, Folder 1)
  - Report to Investment Committee, 1969-1970 (Box 30, Folder 1-6)
  - Investment Committee Minutes, 1966-1970 (Box 34, Folder 7)
  - Examining Committee Minutes, 1937-1949 (Box 34, Folder 8)
  - Examinating Committee, 1965 (Box 35, Folder 1)
  - Minutes of Advisory Committee on Investments, 1965 (Box 35, Folder 2)
  - Minutes of Investment Committee, 1965 (Box 35, Folder 3)
  - Building Committee Minutes and Construction of New Building, undated (Box 43, Folder 4)
  - Retirement Committee Reports to Board of Trustees (w gaps), 1957-1968 (Box 43, Folder 6)
  - Report to Board of Trustees, 1969-1970 (Box 47, Folder 1-2)
  - South Brooklyn Saving Institution Finance Committee No. 4, 1913-1919 (Box 50)
  - South Brooklyn Saving Institution Finance Committee No. 5, 1929-1933 (Box 50)
  - South Brooklyn Saving Institution Finance Committee No. 3, 1897-1914 (Box 51)
  - Finance Committee South Brooklyn Saving Institution, 1860-1896 (Box 51)
- Series 2: Financial records, 1850-2000; 15023
  The series contains financial records and reports dating from 1850 to 2000. It includes financial ledgers, tax documents, Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation reports, NYS Bank exampinations, reports to the Board of Trustees, and financial statements.
  Arrangement
  The series is generally arranged chronologically by date.
  - Contracts SBSB and Various Mortgage Guarentee Cos, 1833 (Box 49, Folder 1)
  - Monthly Reports ledger, 1850-1901; 15072 (Box 12, Folder -)
  - Organizational and financial ledger, circa 1895-1931; 15068 (Box 10, Folder -)
    General
    Ledger contains a mix of organizational and financial records. The following items are listed in its index: Organization of bank, Trustees when elected, Offices, Interest to depositors, Panics, Amount due depositors, Bonds and mortgages, Employees of bank, Finances committees, Executive committees, Examining committees, Interest on securities, and Receipt and payments from 1850
  - Misc Bond Accounts, 1917-1921 (Box 47, Folder 3)
  - Report of Surplus and Undivided Profits, 1920-1922 (Box 29, Folder 1)
  - Report of Surplus and Undivided Profits, 1934-1938 (Box 29, Folder 2-7)
  - Trial Balances, 1931-1947 (Box 47, Folder 4)
  - Contracts SBSB and Various Mortgage Holders, 1933-1934 (Box 49, Folder 2)
  - Financial journal, 1933; 15071 (Box 12, Folder -)
  - Petty Cash ledger, 1933-1934; 15060 (Box 9, Folder -)
  - Daily Record ledger, 1944; 15069 (Box 11, Folder -)
  - Daily Record ledger, 1946; 15070 (Box 11, Folder -)
  - Expense journal - Tax subdivision - Bank buildings and operation, 1944; 15059 (Box 9, Folder -)
  - Tax documents, 1923-1934; 15039 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - U.S. Corporate Federal Income Tax Returns, 1952-1954; 15040 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - FDIC reports and working papers (5 folders), 1943-1971; 15041 (Box 3, Folder 3-7)
  - FDIC reports and working papers (8 folders), 1969-1975; 15042 (Box 4, Folder 1-8)
  - Reports (5 folders), 1958-1981; 15043 (Box 5, Folder 1-5)
  - Financial statements, 1960-1992, 2000; 15044 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation, 1959 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Report Of Examination, 1947-1949 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation, 1944-1946 (Box 21, Folder 3-4)
  - Banking Dept., 1949-1960 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Report Of Examination, 1950-1959 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - State Banking Dept. Examination, 1944 (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Banking Dept. Interim Reports Worksheets, 1964-1968 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Banking Dept.Examination, 1947 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - NY State Banking Dept. Examinations, 1969-1970 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Annual Banking Dept. Reports, 1966-1971 (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - N.Y.S. Banking Dept. Annual Reports, 1974-1975 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - N.Y.S. Banking Dept. Quarterly Reports and Workpapers, 1974-1975 (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Quarterly Banking Dept. Reports, 1971 (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - NY State Banking Dept. Examinations, 1971-1972 (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Banking Dept.Reports Quarterly, 1963-1969 (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - N.Y.S. Banking Dept. Quarterly Reports and worksheets, 1972-1973 (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Bonds Purchased, 1935 (Box 31, Folder 5)
  - Bonds Sold, Bonds Purchased, 1936 (Box 31, Folder 6)
  - Report of Dormant Accounts, 1930-1933 (Box 32, Folder 3-4)
  - Mortgage Account, 1958 (Box 32, Folder 6)
  - Special Account, 1958 (Box 32, Folder 7)
  - First National City Bank Accounts, 1958 (Box 32, Folder 8)
  - Teller's Account, 1958 (Box 32, Folder 9)
  - Treasurer's Report, 1957-1958 (Box 32, Folder 1-2)
  - Report of the Condition, 1929-1932 (Box 33, Folder 1-6)
  - Report of the Condition, 1932-1935 (Box 34, Folder 1-3)
  - Semi-annual Report of the Condition, 1933-1937 (Box 40, Folder 4-8)
  - Quarterly Reports, 1938 (Box 40, Folder 2)
  - Report on Examination of Condition, 1947-1951 (Box 43, Folder 5)
  - Report of Examination, 1952-1956 (Box 44, Folder 1-4)
  - Money Order Account, 1957-1958 (Box 32, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous Accounts, 1954-1958 (Box 32, Folder 11)
  - Life Insurance Data and Permanent Record, 1965 (Box 34, Folder 4-6)
  - US Corporate Income Tax Worksheets, 1965-1971 (Box 35, Folder 4-5)
  - Mortgage Reserve Record, 1944 (Box 36, Folder 1)
  - NYS Franchise Tax Return and Worksheets, 1944-1951 (Box 36, Folder 2-3)
  - NYS Franchise Tax Return, 1959-1966 (Box 36, Folder 6)
  - US Corporation Tax Return, 1955-1960 (Box 37, Folder 2-4)
  - ORE/MIPC Bad Debt Losses RE: Fed Inc Tax, 1967-1973 (Box 36, Folder 4-5)
  - ORE/MIPC Bad Debt Losses RE: Fed Inc Tax, 1974-1975 (Box 37, Folder 1)
  - NYS Franchise Tax and NYC Financial Corporation Tax, 1966-1971 (Box 37, Folder 5-6)
  - US Corporation Tax Return, 1961-1971 (Box 38, Folder 1-4)
  - NYC Financial Corp Tax Return, 1972-1974 (Box 38, Folder 5)
  - US Franchise Tax Regulations, undated (Box 39, Folder 1)
  - NY Franchise Tax Return, 1963-1966 (Box 39, Folder 2)
  - NY Franchise Tax Return, 1972-1974 (Box 39, Folder 3)
  - US Corporate Income Tax Return, 1957-1958 (Box 39, Folder 4)
  - US Corporate Income Tax, 1967-1970 (Box 39, Folder 5)
  - Misc Worksheets, 1945-1948 (Box 40, Folder 1)
  - Bank Examinations, 1949-1962 (Box 41, Folder 1-9)
  - Report of the Condition, 1938 (Box 40, Folder 3)
  - Report of Examination of Life Insurance Dept, 1951 (Box 44, Folder 5)
  - Proceedings of SBTC as Trustee of Mutual Sanvings Banks Fund, 1954-1956 (Box 44, Folder 6)
  - Rpt on Exam. Of Cash, Securities, US Savings Bonds, Travelers Checks, 1949 (Box 44, Folder 7)
  - Valuation of Retirement Plan, 1953-1968 (Box 46, Folder 3-5)
  - Employee Retirement Plan Report on Examination, 1955-1959 (Box 46, Folder 6)
- Series 3: Administrative files, 1883-2006; 14830
  The series represents a small collection of files which were produced by the Board of Trustees and various administrative departments throughout the history of the bank, dating from 1883 to 2006.
  It contains property titles (1886-1892), public relations and advertising files (1937-2005), building and renovation files (1930-1977), copies of 1850 and 1859 articles of incorporaton, one file on the 2006 acquisition of the Independence Community Bank Corporation by Sovereign Bancorp, Inc., and other documents.
  The series is arranged chronologically by date.
  - SBSB Progess Report, 1850-1964 (Box 49)
  - Correspondence with NY State Superintendent of Banking Department, 1883; 15020 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Property titles, 1886-1892; 15021 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Organizational and financial ledger, circa 1895-1931; 15067 (Box 10, Folder -)
  - Franchise Tax Communications, 1920-1921 (Box 32, Folder 5)
  - Banking Department Communications, 1924-1934 (Box 28, Folder 4)
  - Branch Authorizations, 1930, 1957; 15022 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 6422/24 18th Ave Branch Office Misc, 1931 (Box 48, Folder 5)
  - 6422/24 18th Ave Branch Office Misc, 1932-1977 (Box 48, Folder 6)
  - Remsen House Deed/Title, 1936 (Box 48, Folder 3)
  - Ephemera, 1936-1961; 15024 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1771 65th Street Banch Office Misc, 1939 (Box 48, Folder 4)
  - Public Relations manual, 1937; 15025 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 6414/16 18th Ave Branch Office Misc, 1939-1968 (Box 48, Folder 7)
  - Certificate SBSB as Depository for Court and Trust Funds in NYC, 1942 (Box 48, Folder 1)
  - Building Committee Minutes, 1945-1953 (Box 48, Folder 2)
  - Publications, 1945-1952; 15026 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Dormant Account Methods and Procedures survey, 1946; 15027 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - A Study Relating to the Monthly Publication of the South Brooklyn Savings Bank, 1947; 15028 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Retirement System, 1947; 15029 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Advertising - 100th Anniversary, 1949-1950; 15030 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Retirement Plan Survey, 1952 (Box 43, Folder 8)
  - Educational materials, 1952; 15031 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Completed contracts, 1952-1958; 15032 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Report to Building Committee Newkirk Plaza Office, 1958 (Box 47, Folder 8)
  - Building Committee, 1957-1969; 15033 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 1850 Act of Incorporation, 1859 amendment, and 1930 name change certificates, 1958; 15034 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Retirement Plan Report of Examination, 1962 (Box 43, Folder 7)
  - Branch Sites Committee Final Report Newkirk Plaza Office, 1964 (Box 47, Folder 6)
  - Main office alterations, 1964; 15035 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Branch Sites Committee Final Report Murray Hill Office, 1970 (Box 47, Folder 7)
  - Branch Sites Committee Final Report Parkchester Office, 1972 (Box 47, Folder 5)
  - Specifications for Alterations to Parkchester Building, 1972 (Box 47, Folder 9)
  - Mike Armstrong - Advertising files, 1975-2005; 15036 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Financial planning, 2006; 15037 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Stockholders - Merger meeting, 2006; 15038 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Series 4: Photographs and Scrapbooks, 1883-2001; 14831
  The series contains photographs and scrapbooks documenting the bank from 1883 to 2001.
  It includes numerous photographic portraits of bank trustees, in three albums, five folders, and one framed photograph (circa 1940-2001). Additionally, the series contains two scrapbooks documenting the lives of trustees (1922-1982).
  It contains two clippings scrapbooks (1883-1920) and five advertising scrapbooks (1931-1953).
  Other photographs include bank baseball teams (circa 1930), the corner of Atlantic Avenue and Court Street (circa 1920), the bank's 90th anniversary (1940), Christmas celebrations (1951-1952), and bank openings (circa 1960).
  - Corner of Atlantic Avenue and Court Street photographs, circa 1920; 15081 (Box 17, Folder -)
  - South Brooklyn Savings Bank baseball team, circa 1930; 15046 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - 90th anniversary photographs, 1940; 15083 (Box 17, Folder -)
  - Bank opening photographs (2 folders), circa 1960; 15047 (Box 6, Folder 2-3)
  - Christmas photographs, 1951-1952; 15048 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Board of Trustees portraits (3 folders), 1959-1979, 2001; 15049 (Box 6, Folder 5-7)
  - Board of Trustees oversize portraits, 1970s; 15080 (Box 17, Folder -)
  - Board of Trustees group photograph, 1975; 15050 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Trustees at NASDAQ MarketSite, Times Square (framed), circa 2000; 15079 (Box 16, Folder -)
  - Board of Trustees portrait albums (3 albums), circa 1940-1972; 15051 (Box 7, Folder -)
    Albums feature portraits of Board of Trustees dating back to 1850. The first and second albums appear to have been created around 1940, with additional material added to the albums until around 1972.
  - Board of Trustees scrapbooks (2 scrapbooks), 1922-1982; 15054 (Box 8, Folder -)
  - Clippings scrapbook, 1883-1923; 15055 (Box 8, Folder -)
  - Clippings scrapbook, 1917-1918; 15066 (Box 10, Folder -)
  - Advertising scrapbook, 1931-1937; 15078 (Box 16, Folder -)
  - Advertising and publicity scrapbook, 1943-1949; 15075 (Box 15, Folder -)
  - Advertising scrapbooks (3 scrapbooks), 1951-1953; 15076 (Box 15, Folder -)
- Series 5: Memorabilia, circa 1920s-2004; 14832
  The series contains bank memorabilia, dating from around the 1920s to 2004. It primarily consists of objects relating the bank's sports teams, including trophies for Brooklyn bank baseball, basketball, and bowling leagues (1930s and 1970s). Other objects include a wood block stamp of the bank's 18th Avenue branch building (circa 1920s-1940s), radio advertisment 12" vinyl records (circa 1950s), advertising awards (1970s), and paperweights commemorating the bank's stock valuations (1992-2004).
  - South Brooklyn Savings Bank 18th Avenue office building wood block stamp, circa 1920s-1940s; 15084 (Box 17)
  - South Brooklyn Savings Bank championship team signed baseballs (2 objects), 1933-1934; 15063 (Box 19)
  - Savings Bank Baseball League of Brooklyn trophy, 1933-1935; 15061 (Object Artifact shelf)
  - Savings Bank Baseball League of Brooklyn championship trophy, 1936; 15057 (Object Artifact shelf)
  - Savings Bank Basketball League of Brooklyn championship trophy, 1934-1935; 15058 (Object Artifact shelf)
  - Savings Bank Bowling League 2nd place trophy, 1976-1977; 15062 (Object Artifact shelf)
  - Radio advertisements 12" vinyl records (2 records), circa 1950s; 15082 (Box 17)
  - Eighth Annual Addy Awards - 1st place certificate, 1976; 15077 (Box 16)
  - Financial Advertising and Marketing Association - Town Crier Award, 1975; 15056 (Object Artifact shelf)
  - Commemorative paperweights (10 objects), 1992-2004; 15085 (Box 18)
  - Advertisements, circa 1950s (Box 16)
- Series 6: Unprocessed Material (Box 20)